here is everything you need to know
about the new Commander bracket system
beta now I want to preface this and
remind you all that Commander is a
casual format and you can play it
however you want with your play group if
you already have an established set of
house rules with your friends you're
more than welcome to keep doing that and
ignore this video completely of course
you're more than welcome to take some
ideas from this system and try them out
for yourself so what is the bracket
system even a to do put simply it's
giving players a better way to define
the power levels of their decks and have
a better time finding the types of
commander games they want to play with
people who they might not have played
with before the easiest example of this
in action today is
cedh If you join a pod playing cedh you
know exactly what you're walking into
and what to expect from the game there's
no rule zero conversation required your
you're about to see the best cards
Combos and the most optimized decks you
understand that winning is the first
priority for the majority of cedh
players it's extremely unlikely you're
going to find a Barefoot themed deck
here so now imagine this but for all
sorts of power levels of decks no longer
will everyone's deck just be a seven
this bracket system is by no means
perfect and no doubt some players will
even a lie about the contents of their
deck or look to build Decks that are on
the top end of one bracket and are a
literal bees KNE cap away from falling
into the next bracket to try and gain an
edge on everybody but for the vast
majority of players and the majority of
the time it will help you get into the
games you want to play faster finally
don't forget that this is a beta this is
something that has been in discussions
for months but we're just 18 people on
the cfp out of millions of people that
play Commander around the world there's
no doubt going to be some changes to the
system in the future and that's why we
want you to start trying out this system
and letting us know your feedback good
or bad if you want to pass on any
feedback you can leave your comments on
this video down below you can email me
or you can DM me on blue sky or Twitter
before we get into the brackets I think
it's really important to cover some
definitions of the terms I'll be using
to make sure we're all on the same page
to start we have the brackets these are
effectively the tiers that Commander
decks will fall into based on their play
style or certain cards that are within
the deck next we have the band list this
is a list of cards that are completely
banned from play in Commander as of this
beta we're using the current current ban
list and no changes have been made to it
more on that
later next there's Mass Land denial
these are cards that regularly destroy
Exile bounce perpetually keep tapped or
change what Mana is produced by four or
more lands per player without replacing
them examples of this are Armageddon
suer winter orb and blood moon basically
any card or common game plan that messes
with several people's lands or the Mana
they
produce and lastly there's the game
changer list it's been here the whole
time and is new to the beta the game
changers list is a list of cards that
the cfp have agreed are too powerful for
casual social games of Commander when
they're played in casual pods they
usually Garner a collective grown from
the table cards like turrid God of
fright cyclonic Rift smothering tith and
ristic study it also features cards that
are practically considered cedh Staples
you have fast Mana like ancient tomb
manav Vault and lion ey Diamond premium
tutors like demonic chor mystical chor
and survival of the fittest and there's
a handful of extremely efficient combo
and stack pieces like Fus Oracle drth
magistrate and ad nauseum there are 40
cards in total on this list now remember
this list is not a Bann list but they
can certainly be considered to be a
watch list and if any cards ever get
unbanned in the future they'll likely
find themselves on this list to begin
with and if nardu Second Coming ever
gets printed again you can rest assured
they'll end up on this list before
potentially ending up on the band
list okay let's take a quick look at all
the brackets overall as this is
important to show what we're trying to
achieve and then we'll dive into each
one so there are five brackets in total
bracket one is exhibition bracket two is
core bracket 3 is upgraded bracket 4 is
optimized and bracket 5 is
cedh as you can probably tell these
brackets go from what are objectively
low power decks all the way up to what
are considered the highest powered decks
here's the important part the first
three brackets are considered to be the
social brackets whereas the last two
brackets are the competitive brackets
again this comes back to being able to
give players the tools to find the games
close to what they're looking
for let's go through each of the
brackets and the rules associated with
them bracket one
exhibition this bracket is meant for the
ultimate casual decks I think it would
be fair to say that this could be
considered the vorthos tier
here you're going to find Decks that
might only consist of cards that feature
the weather light crew or Decks that
have strict building requirements like
everything must have two attack or cost
two Mana the games here are likely to be
slow but the main focus is having fun
and players showing off their unique
creations for decks to be considered
bracket one they must contain no cards
from the game changer list no
intentional two card infinite combos
Mass Land denial or extra turn spells
and Shooters should be far and few
between to clarify what we mean by no
intentional two card infinit is if you
happen to steal some cards from your
opponents via a ganty or other means and
then assemble a combo there that's
totally allowed actively building your
deck with two specific cards to combo is
not allowed bracket two
core this is where practically every
prepackaged precon deck sits they're not
perfect by any means but there's going
to be some good synergies that can set
you up for some big turns the deck is
not completely optimized because you've
no doubt kept in your pet cards that you
want to add to every deck mine is elixir
of
immortality I think the perfect example
of this is the Stella Lee precon from
Outlaws of Thunder Junction it's a
clunky spellslinger deck but with the
right pilot a bit of planning and a
pinch of luck it can do its thing and
have an explosive turn or
two decks in this bracket are unlikely
to win the game out of nowhere but will
likely have a clear winner by turn 10 or
so for decks to be considered bracket 2
they must contain no cards from the game
changer list no intentional two card
infinite combos or Mass Land denial
extra turn spells should only appear in
low quantities and not intended to be
changed in succession or looped and as
with bracket one tutors should be
sparse bracket three
upgraded this is where you'll find Decks
that are starting to become a bit more
competitive as the name suggest you'll
find a lot of upgraded precons here it's
also the first tier that allows you to
play cards from the game changer list
upgraded bracket decks are allowed to
run up to three cards from the game
changer list and with the these upgrades
you'll likely find that games go a bit
quicker and could potentially end the
game out of nowhere two card infinite
combos are allowed here but not early
game two card combos no thesis Oracle
into demonic consultation will be found
here as with the previous bracket extra
turn spells are also allowed as long as
they're not chained together or looped
and this is the last bracket where Mass
Land destruction is banned onto bracket
four
optimized here is the first of the two
competitive brackets expect decks in
this bracket to focus mostly on winning
but that's not to say someone's slime
Against Humanity deck won't become a
force to be reckoned with powerful
versions of players favorite commanders
are to be found here as opposed to Toran
and metad deex which can be found in the
final bracket combos extra turn spells
and Mass Land destruction are all
welcome here in the optimized bracket
the only restriction is the band list
and finally we have bracket 5 the cedh
bracket there's not much to say about
this bracket as anyone who knows what
cedh is knows what to expect from this
bracket this is the highest power of
commander games you'll ever see winning
is a top priority for most players and
it's entirely possible that some games
might be over on the first or second
turn again the only restriction here is
the band list let's quickly recap
brackets 1 through three are designed
for more social and fun games whereas
brackets four and five are designed with
a more competitive Focus brackets 3 four
and five is where game Cher cards are
allowed with bracket 3 having the
Restriction of only three game Cher
cards allowed speaking of the game
changer list on the list we have drth
magistrate enlightened shoor Sarah
sanctum smothering tith trouble impair
cyclonic Rift extra appropriate force of
will Fierce guardianship ristic study
F's Oracle öa Lord H High artificer
mystical Tudor jinx's core orer Bolis of
Citadel demonic chor Imperial seal
opposition agent turd got of fright
vampiric Tudor adium J SK will
underworld breach gu's cradle survival
of the fittest ven clicks voice of
hunger the One Ring trinisphere Chrome
mops grim lion ey Diamond MOX Diamond
man ofal ancient tomb glacial Chasm the
Tabernacle at pend Veil kinan Bond's
Prodigy uro tiger Shadow wioo Joiner of
forces and Grand Arbiter Augustine IV
now keep in mind this list is not set in
stone if you believe a card should be on
this list be sure to let us know via any
of the feedback channels if you want to
see the reasons for why each card is on
the game changers list be sure to read
Gavin's article which I've linked below
now don't forget if your commander
happens to be on the game changers list
that does count towards your game
changer count in Brackets 3 having said
that rule zero can still come into play
here if your urer commander is pivotal
to your brother's W deck so that's all
the brackets and the game changers what
now ideally you'll start playing and
building decks with the bracket system
and let us know what you think moxfield
and Ed H Rec should all have tools in
place by the time this video goes live
to help you build within certain
brackets I'll also be looking to upload
some deck texts with the brackets in
mind so stay tuned for them you can even
check out the decks I've made already
with brackets on my moxfield
account now as far as for the next
update we're looking to roll out the
full system and some potential unband in
April so let me know what you think of
this system down below along with any
questions you might have if you learned
something this video be sure to give it
a like And subscribe because if you
don't Sam Reich will be waiting for you
thanks for watching and I'll see you in
the next one